Finding aid to the Deb Friedman collection of DC Rape Crisis Center records SSC.MS.00795
Sophia Smith Collection
Deb Friedman collection of DC Rape Crisis Center records
1971-1984
Sophia Smith Collection
Rape Crisis Center (Washington, D.C.)
SSC.MS.00795
.5 linear feet (2 half document boxes)
The D.C. Rape Crisis Center was founded in 1972 as one of the first rape crisis centers in the country, and the only center at the time run primarily by and for women of color. This collection contains orientation information for new volunteers, as well as event information, various publications, and pamphlets. Addition material includes handwritten notes (loose and in notebooks), largely by Deb Friedman, on Feminist Alliance Against Rape (FAAR) and AEGIS meeting proceedings, as well as newsletters, agendas, and member phone/mailing lists which provide direct evidence of the work of these organizations.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
These records were collected and donated by Deb Friedman to the Sophia Smith Collection.
Biographical / Historical
The D.C. Rape Crisis Center was founded in 1972 as one of the first rape crisis centers in the country, and the only center at the time run primarily by and for women of color. The center provides a range of resources for survivors, both in person and through a volunteer-run hotline, including counseling, information on their rights and health, and advice for speaking to the police and making a case. The center also provides education on rape and rape prevention (including self-defense classes) to the community at large. No legislation existed at the time of the center's founding to protect or defend rape survivors, so a large portion of their work focused on political lobbying and grassroots activism. Their mission statement today describes them as, "committed to the health and wellness of people with layered identities and complex needs," as they, "work to inform, equip and engage stakeholders in eradicating sexual violence. In our 43rd year, we are working to power a culture of consent and leading the world in insistently imagining a world without rape."
See their website here: http://dcrcc.org/
The Feminist Alliance Against Rape (FAAR) was formed as a sub-group of the DC Rape Crisis Center in 1974 as a way to network among feminists in the anti-rape movement. FAAR published a monthly newsletter that invited others to join the discussion on violence against women and provided resources and practical information for grassroots organizers. Later, FAAR combined efforts with the National Coalition Network for the Elimination of Violence Against Women (NCN) in Wisconsin and the Alliance Against Sexual Coercion (AASC) in Boston to publish Aegis: Magazine on Ending Violence Against Women, which ran until 1977.
Related Materials
In the Periodicals collections, see: Aegis - Magazine on Ending Violence Against Women (formerly Feminist Alliance Against Rape Newsletter).
See also the Loretta Ross papers.
Content Description
Includes information on marches sponsored by the Center, the contents of an orientation packet, various pamphlets and publications by the Center, four issues of Black Belt Woman magazine, photocopied articles, and a workbook for children.
Additions to the collection include handwritten notes (loose and in notebooks), largely by Deb Friedman, on FAAR meeting proceedings, as well as notes on Aegis newsletters, agendas, and member phone/mailing lists, all of which reflect the work of these groundbreaking efforts to address issues around violence against women.
D.C. Rape Crisis Center -- History; Rape--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Women -- Violence against -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Friedman, Deb; Friedman, Deb; Friedman, Deb; Feminist Alliance Against Rape (U.S.)
- Deb Friedman collection of DC Rape Crisis Center records, 2018-S-0061
  - Events: Take Back the Night, March to Stop Violence Against Women information and poster, 1976-1981; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Orientation packet: "Crisis Counseling," "Rights of Rape Victims," plus folder, approximately 1975; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Orientation packet: D.C. Rape Crisis Center staff information, approximately 1975; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Orientation packet: photocopies of articles about rape, approximately 1971-1975; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Orientation packet: "Politics of Rape" by the D.C. Rape Crisis Center, approximately 1975; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Orientation packet: "Politics of Rape" by Susan Griffin, approximately 1975; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Orientation packet: "Rape Prevention Tactics" paper and two pamphlets (English and Spanish), approximately 1975-1980; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Orientation packet: testimony by the D.C. Rape Crisis Center to the Public Safety Committee Task Force on Rape, 18 September 1973; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Orientation packet: venereal disease and pregnancy information, approximately 1975; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets: "Facts About Rape", approximately 1980; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets: "Rape: A Reference for Women in D.C.", 1974, 1975, approximately 1980; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets: "Staying Safe" workbook for children on sexual assault, 1984; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Publications: "Black Belt Woman" magazine, Vol 1, Issues 1, 3, 5, 6, 1975-1976; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Publications: "How to Start a Rape Crisis Center", 1972, 1973; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Publications: "How to Start a Rape Crisis Center: Revised and Expanded second edition", 1977; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
- Deb Friedman collection of Feminist Alliance Against Rape (FAAR) records, 2018-S-0086; Feminist Alliance Against Rape (U.S.); .25 linear feet (1 half legal document box)
  Scope and Contents
  Handwritten notes (loose and in notebooks), largely by Deb Friedman, on Feminist Alliance Against Rape (FAAR) and AEGIS meeting proceedings, as well as newsletters, agendas, and member phone/mailing lists which provide direct evidence of the work of these organizations. See the Periodical collection for actual copies of Aegis - Magazine on Ending Violence Against Women (formerly Feminist Alliance Against Rape Newsletter).
  - Notebooks: FAAR and AEGIS meeting notes, 1975-1980; 3 folders (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Loose notes on meetings, agendas (handwritten), 1977-1978; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - FAAR and AEGIS meeting agendas, memos (typed), 1977-1979; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)